




	
	
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Game Math on K-State CIS 580 Textbook</title>
    <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/index.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Game Math on K-State CIS 580 Textbook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:05 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/01-introduction/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/01-introduction/index.html</guid>
      <description>Math plays a very large role in computer games, as math is used both in the process of simulating game worlds (i.e. to calculate game physics) and in the rendering of the same (i.e. to represent and rasterize 3D objects). Algebra and trigonometry play a vital role in nearly every game&amp;rsquo;s logic. However, vectors, matricies, and quaternions play an especially important role in hardware-accelerated 3D rendering.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coordinate Systems</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/02-coordinate-systems/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/02-coordinate-systems/index.html</guid>
      <description>Computer games almost universally take place in a simulated 2D or 3D world. We use coordinate systems to represent the position of various objects within these worlds. Perhaps the simplest coordinate system is one you encountered in elementary school - the number line:
The number line represents a 1-dimensional coordinate system - its coordinates are a single value that range from $ -\infty $ to $ \infty $. We normally express this as a single number.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trigonometry</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/03-trigonometry/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/03-trigonometry/index.html</guid>
      <description>Trigonometry - the math that deals with the side lengths and angles of triangles, plays an important role in many games. The trigonometric functions Sine, Cosine, and Tangent relate to the ratios of sides in a right triangle:
$$ \sin{A} = \frac{opposite}{hypotenuse} = \frac{a}{c} \tag{0} $$ $$ \cos{A} = \frac{adjacent}{hypotenuse} = \frac{b}{c} \tag{1} $$ $$ \tan{A} = \frac{opposite}{adjacent} = \frac{a}{b} \tag{2} $$ You can use the System.MathF library to compute $ \sin $, $ \cos $ using float values:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vectors</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/04-vectors/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/b-game-math.md/04-vectors/index.html</guid>
      <description>Games almost universally use vectors to represent coordinates rather than points, as these have additional mathematical properties which can be very helpful. In mathematical notation, vectors are expressed similar to points, but use angle brackets, i.e.: $ $ and $ $ for two- and three-element vectors. A vector represents both direction and magnitude, and relates to the trigonometric right triangle. Consider the case of a two-element vector - the vector is the hypotenuse of a right triangle with adjacent leg formed by its X component and opposite leg formed by its Y component.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>