




	
	
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
		

	
	
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		

	
	
		
		
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Heightmap Terrain on K-State CIS 580 Textbook</title>
    <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/index.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Heightmap Terrain on K-State CIS 580 Textbook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Mar 2020 10:53:05 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/01-introduction/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/01-introduction/index.html</guid>
      <description>Now that we understand how 3D worlds are built from triangle meshes, and how we can use cameras to explore those worlds, let&amp;rsquo;s start putting those ideas to work. In this section, we&amp;rsquo;ll focus on creating terrain from a heightmap - a grayscale bitmap representing the changing elevation of the ground.
Like our earlier examples, we&amp;rsquo;ll start from a starter project with our assets pre-loaded. In addition, we&amp;rsquo;ll include the ICamera interface and the FPSCamera we created in the lesson on Lights and Cameras .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heightmaps</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/02-heightmaps/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/02-heightmaps/index.html</guid>
      <description>You might be wondering just what a heightmap is. If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever used a topographic map , you&amp;rsquo;ve seen a similar idea. Contour maps include contour lines_, lines that trace when the ground reaches a certain altitude. Inside the line is higher than that altitude, and outside of the line is lower (or visa-versa). The contours themselves are typically marked with the altitude they represent.
A heightmap is similar, but instead of using lines, each pixel in the map represents a square section of land, and the color value at that point indicates the average altitude of that square.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terrain Class</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/03-terrain-class/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/03-terrain-class/index.html</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ll start with the class definition:
/// &amp;lt;summary&amp;gt; /// A class representing terrain /// &amp;lt;/summary&amp;gt; public class Terrain { // The game this Terrain belongs to Game game; }As with most of our classes, we&amp;rsquo;ll keep a reference to the Game object to access the shared ContentManager and GraphicsDevice.
Class Fields We could store our heightmap directly, but all we really need out of it are the height values, and these need to be scaled.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using the Terrain</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/04-using-the-terrain/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/04-using-the-terrain/index.html</guid>
      <description>Let&amp;rsquo;s see our terrain in action. First we&amp;rsquo;ll need to make some changes in our Game1 class. We&amp;rsquo;ll add a Terrain field:
// The terrain Terrain terrain;In our Game1.LoadContent(), we&amp;rsquo;ll load the heightmap and construct our terrain:
// Build the terrain Texture2D heightmap = Content.Load&amp;lt;Texture2D&amp;gt;(&amp;#34;heightmap&amp;#34;); terrain = new Terrain(this, heightmap, 10f, Matrix.Identity);And in our Game1.Draw() we&amp;rsquo;ll render it with the existing camera:
// Draw the terrain terrain.Draw(camera);Now if you run the game, you should see your terrain, and even be able to move around it using the camera controls (WASD + Mouse).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolating Heights</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/05-interpolating-heights/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/05-interpolating-heights/index.html</guid>
      <description>While you can now walk over your terrain, you probably notice that the camera seems really jittery. Why isn&amp;rsquo;t it smooth?
Think about how we render our terrain. The diagram below shows the terrain in one dimension. At each integral step, we have a height value. The terrain (represented by green lines) is interpolated between these heights.
Now think about what our function transforming world coordinates to heights is doing. It casts tx to an int to throw away the fractional part of the coordinate in order to get an array index.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summary</title>
      <link>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/06-summary/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2020 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ksu-cs-textbooks.github.io/cis580/15-heightmap-terrain/06-summary/index.html</guid>
      <description>Now you&amp;rsquo;ve seen the basics of creating a terrain from a heightmap. Armed with this knowledge, you can create an outdoor game world. You can find or create additional heightmaps to add new terrains to your game. You can swap the textures to create different kinds of environments as well.
But you could also create an even larger worlds by using multiple terrains and stitching them together at the edges - a technique often called terrain patches.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>