




  
	
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Introduction to MonoGame :: K-State CIS 580 Textbook</title>
    <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/</link>
    <description>One Framework to Rule them All</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 11:41:07 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/01-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/01-introduction/</guid>
      <description>In this class we are using the MonoGame framework to build our game projects. MonoGame is an open-source, cross-platform framework built on C# and .NET. I like to use it for this course because it is truly a framework, not a game engine. Rather, it supplies tools that provides abstractions for some of the more technically challenging details of developing game software in a non-opinionated manner.&#xA;From the developer standpoint, there are several clear benefits:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Game Class</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/02-the-game-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/02-the-game-class/</guid>
      <description>At the heart of an XNA project is a class that inherits from Game. This class handles initializing the graphics device, manages components, and most importantly, implements the game loop.&#xA;The MonoGame Game Loop As you saw in Game Programming Patterns:&#xA;A game loop runs continuously during gameplay. Each turn of the loop, it processes user input without blocking, updates the game state, and renders the game. It tracks the passage of time to control the rate of gameplay.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Game Window</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/03-the-game-window/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/03-the-game-window/</guid>
      <description>While MonoGame does support 3D rendering, we’re going to start with 2D games. When working in 2D, MonoGame uses a coordinate system similar to the screen coordinates you’ve seen in your earlier classes. The origin of the coordinate system $ (0, 0) $, is the upper-left corner of the game window’s client area, and the X-axis increases to the right and the Y-axis increases downward.&#xA;The part of the game world that appears on-screen is determined by the active viewport, represented by a Viewport struct - basically a rectangle plus a minimum and maximum depth.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Game Initialization</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/04-game-initialization/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/04-game-initialization/</guid>
      <description>Before we actually move into the game loop, we need to initialize the game - load all of its needed parts and set all initial values. The MonoGame Game class provides two virtual hook methods for doing this: Game.Initialize() and Game.LoadContent().&#xA;You might be wondering why we have two methods, or asking why the constructor is not included in this count. These are all good questions. First, in the documentation we see that Initialize():</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Update Method</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/05-the-update-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/05-the-update-method/</guid>
      <description>As we mentioned before, the virtual Game.Update(GameTime gameTime) method is a hook for adding your game’s logic. By overriding this method, and adding your own game logic code, you fulfill the update step of the game loop.&#xA;This is where you place the simulation code for your game - where the world the game is representing is updated. Here, all your actors (the parts of the game world that move and interact) are updated.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Draw Method</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/06-the-draw-method/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/06-the-draw-method/</guid>
      <description>The Game.Draw(Game.Update(GameTime gameTime) method is a another hook, this one for adding your game’s rendering code. By overriding this method, and adding your own rendering code, you fulfill the draw step of the game loop.&#xA;MonoGame uses the graphics hardware to render the scene, along with double buffering. Thus, when we render, we are drawing into a back buffer, and once that drawing is complete, we flip the buffers so that the one we just finished is what ends up being rendered on-screen, and we now can start drawing into the next back buffer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Summary</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/07-summary/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/01-intro-to-monogame/07-summary/</guid>
      <description>In this chapter we looked at how MonoGame implements the Game Loop pattern within its Game class. We also saw how the Game class interacts with the GameWindow class, which provides an abstraction of the operating system’s window representation. We saw how we can add our own custom code into the MonoGame game loop by overriding the Game.Update() and Game.Draw() methods, as well as the overriding Game.Initialize() and Game.LoadContent() to set up the game world.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>