




  
	
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
	  

  
	
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
	  

  
	
		
		
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Audio :: K-State CIS 580 Textbook</title>
    <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/</link>
    <description>Chapter 5 Audio Get your games rocking!</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 11:41:07 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/01-introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/01-introduction/</guid>
      <description>We often focus on the visual aspects of games, but the audio aspects can really make a game shine. Consider that many game tracks are now presented as orchestral performances:&#xA;And how important sound effects can be for conveying what is happening in a game?&#xA;In this chapter, we will explore both sound effects and music, and how to implement them within MonoGame.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sound Effects</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/02-sound-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/02-sound-effects/</guid>
      <description>From the “bing” of a coin box in Super Mario Bros to the reveal chimes of the Zelda series, sound effects provide a powerful mechanism for informing the player of what is happening in your game world.&#xA;SoundEffect Class MonoGame represents sound effects with the SoundEffect class. Like other asset types, we don’t normally construct this directly, we rather load it through the content pipeline. Usually, a sound effect will start as a .</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positional Sounds</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/03-positional-sounds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/03-positional-sounds/</guid>
      <description>Positional sounds provide the illusion of depth and movement by using panning, doppler shift, and other techniques to emulate the affect movement and distance have on sounds. Positional sounds can convey important information in games, especially when combined with surround-sound speakers and headphones.&#xA;To create positional sound effects, we need to place the sound in a 3D (or pseudo 2D) soundscape, which incorporates both a listener (i.e. the player) and an emitter (the source of the sound).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Music</title>
      <link>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/04-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 10:53:26 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://textbooks.cs.ksu.edu/cis580/05-audio/04-music/</guid>
      <description>Music also has a powerful role to play in setting the mood. It can also be used to convey information to the player, as Super Mario Bros does when the remaining time to finish the level falls below 1 minute.&#xA;Song Class While it is possible to play music using a SoundEffect, MonoGame supports music through the Song class. This represents a song loaded from a wav or mp4 file.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>